on this video we are going to talk about
a programming language that i believe
every developer should try at least once
and that is rust rust has been voted as
the most loved programming language for
six years in a row in the stack overflow
developer survey even though it's a
fairly young language compared to c and
c plus plus companies like amazon
cloudflare and microsoft are replacing c
and c plus plus with rust microsoft for
example has been rewriting low level
windows components in rust that used to
be in c and c plus plus and google is a
sponsoring the project that is trying to
bring rust as the second official
programming language of the linux kernel
which right now is based only in c even
intel is investing in working with ross
with the intel principal engineer
calling ross as the future of systems
programming and calling c as the new
assembly assembly being a language that
nobody actually writes on anymore it
also turns out that rust is eco-friendly
as well
rust and c are both 50 percent more
energy efficient than java and they are
more energy efficient than python but it
also turns out that rust code is more
secure than cnc plus plus code microsoft
says that if they use rust instead of c
and c plus plus they would have had 70
percent less security vulnerabilities
that is a lot rust also has a very good
developer experience and that is thanks
to the compiler it has the most helpful
compiler i have ever worked with for
sure the compiler of rust tells you that
the code is wrong but also it explains
to you why
it also tells you how you can fix it and
even sometimes will give you the code to
fix the problem it's amazing if all i
have said today has made you curious to
learn more about rust then please keep
watching because today we are going to
see what makes rust different from other
programming languages what makes it so
special what makes it as fast as c but
safer than c what does safety even mean
in the programming world what can you
build with rust who should learn rust
and we're going to be looking at the
code and compiler as well rust is a low
level programming language that is
focused on being fast and safe let's
start by looking at what low level means
we say that low level programming
languages are closer to the machine and
we say that high level programming
languages are closer to developers to
the way humans speak
from low to high the closest you can get
to the machine would be to write zeros
and ones but nobody does that so instead
we have assembly code assembly code is
literal instructions to the processor
but again nobody does that also so we
have something a little bit higher than
that and that is c and c plus plus then
maybe java would come and then at the
top would be javascript and python for
example what makes a language low or
high level is how many layers of
abstraction there are between the code
that the developer writes and the zeros
and ones that the machine understands if
you look at javascript in the browser
for example it is not a compiled
language and there is many abstraction
levels between javascript code and zeros
and ones because javascript has to be
understood and read by the browser the
browser is programmed maybe on c and c
plus so the browser reads your code the
browser will execute your code and then
the browser will tell the processor what
to do so as you can see there are many
steps between the machine and the code
that you wrote is the same with python
the interpreter of python is written in
c so when you write python code and you
run the code what you are doing is you
are giving your python code to a c
program and that z program is
understanding what you want to do and
that c program isn't talking to the
processor to do what you want to do in
contrast low level languages like c or
ros don't need this translation they
don't need this middleman because when
you finish working with rust or c when
you compile that code the code that you
will get the code that you will run will
be understood by the processor directly
this means there is no middleman between
your code and the computer as you can
imagine because we are closer to the
machine and because the code that we
wrote does not need a middleman to be
understood by the processor our programs
are going to run faster that also means
that our code is going to be more
powerful we are closer to the machine we
are right next to the machine so we can
do whatever we want but that means we
will have to be more careful like uncle
ben says with great power comes great
responsibility in low level languages
like c for example you have to manage
memory by yourself which means that for
example if you want to create a variable
to save a string of text you're going to
have to ask for a space in memory to be
able to put your variable there and when
you are done doing whatever you need to
do with that variable you also have to
remember to free that space in memory if
you just take space and memory and you
forget to free the memory then your
program will run out of memory and crash
if you come from a language like python
or javascript i am sure that this
concept feels very very foreign to you
in javascript or python when we are
using variables we just create variables
we don't have to ask for a space in
memory please we just have to just
create the variable and when we are done
using the variable we just don't do
anything with a variable we don't have
to remember to also free that memory
space now this is not because python and
javascript are magical and they never
run out of memory the reason why they
don't run out of memory is because there
is a magical little guy called the
garbage collector in the background
doing all this memory management for us
the garbage collector is a program that
is looking at your program while it's
running it is looking at the variables
that you create and is looking to see
which variables you don't use anymore if
nothing is pointing to a variable that
means that that variable is garbage so
it will be free from memory when a
programming language has a garbage
collector it will be very comfortable
for developers to write code in that
language because we don't have to think
about allocating any frame memory all
the time but but because of the garbage
collector our program is not going to
run as fast as if it was written in a
programming language like c that does
not have garbage collection now garbage
collection was one of the reasons why
this cord switched from go to rust go
has a garbage collector while rust
doesn't and in the case of discord they
saw some performance spikes happen
because of the garbage collector sea and
rust do not have garbage collectors
which makes them faster but that also
means that developers have to be careful
when they're accessing memory microsoft
says that 70 of the security issues that
they have to fix are related to memory
access memory access box can happen when
for example we access a place in memory
that doesn't exist it hasn't been
allocated or when we're trying to access
a part of memory that has already been
freed or when we free a part of memory
twice all these are mistakes that are
very easy to make and they will result
in a runtime error this is when rust
shines and this is why companies like
ross so much because it maybe is not
faster than c maybe it's not faster than
c plus plus but it is safer than them
providing almost the same performance
which is a huge win in rust we don't
have garbage collection but we also
don't have to allocate a free memory
manually and that's because rust has a
very cool way of thinking about memory
and is a concept called ownership
ownership is one if not the most
important concept to understand when
working with rust it makes you think
about the data in your program in a
different way than what we are used to
if you're using javascript python go or
even c with the concept of ownership the
data of your program is owned by
variables your data can only be owned by
one owner at a time and if the owner is
not in scope or used anymore the data is
dropped from memory if it sounds hard to
understand is because it is it's not a
very easy concept to grasp at the
beginning especially if we're coming
from a garbage collected language like
go javascript or python i won't explain
ownership 100 on this video but i do
want to give you a taste of how
ownership looks like here we have some
rust code with two functions
one is the main function where we are
creating a variable called myname that
holds the text nico the main function is
then calling the say high function and
it's sending the my name as an argument
on the say hi function we just print hi
plus the name that we received after
everything is done in the say hi
function we return to the main function
where we are printing the my name
variable one more time now think for a
second and tell me what do you think the
output would be
we have a variable with a string we give
that variable to a function the function
is going to print that variable on the
console when that function is finished
then we're going to print that variable
again in the console if we are
javascript python or even go developers
what we would expect would be to see
something like this on the output but in
the worst world that would not be
correct
that would not compile at all
this is because after we call the say hi
function with the my name variable as an
argument
the data which is the string that
contains nico is moved
not copied but moved
out of the my name variable into the say
hi function now the say hi function is
the owner of the nico string and the my
name variable in the main function
cannot be used anymore as you can see
with ownership we have to think about
how the data moves in our program in a
different way to what we are used to and
this is one of the reasons why learning
rust is not an easy task at all it has a
very steep learning curve in my opinion
when i learned go for the first time i
felt productive in goal in like a week
or less but i have been writing rose
code for a while now and i cannot really
say that i feel a hundred percent
comfortable with it but thankfully as i
said the rust compiler is super cool and
helpful if you make a mistake it is
going to help you fix that mistake it's
going to teach you it's even going to
give you the code that you need is
awesome if you try to run the code with
the ownership error for example it will
give you a pretty good message of how
the variable was created where was it
moved and where you made a mistake or
for example if you are new to rust and
you want to just print a number in the
console and you do the following code
that code is not going to work but the
error that you're going to see in the
compiler is going to be very helpful it
is going to point out at the place where
the error happened and it's also going
to even give you a helpful message to
tell you what code you might need
awesome so what can you build with rust
personally i am using rust to build
smart contracts for blockchain platforms
like polkadot and solana but people are
using rust to build all sorts of things
you can use rust to build command line
interfaces you could program your back
end in rust there are people writing
software for embedded devices in ros
there's also people making video game
engines in rust and you could even make
a web application in rust if you compile
it to web assembly just because we can
doesn't mean we should it's always
better to think about choosing the right
tool for the job so if you're looking
for raw speed safety and correctness
then i think rust is a very very good
choice if you are already a developer
and you have the time to learn it but if
instead of program speed you are looking
for developer speed but you still want a
language that is faster than python and
javascript then i would say that go is a
very good choice in rust the code runs
fast in go the programmer runs fast if
you are already a developer and you want
to learn go because you're curious you
want to see how fast the language can be
how simple can it be and how easy can it
be to learn then please click the link
below there you're going to find a free
golang course with subtitles in hangout
we're going to see what makes ghost
special what makes it faster than python
or javascript and we're going to build a
tiny project as well so please click the
link below and i will see you there now
coming back to rust even if you don't
have a use case right now for rust even
if you don't have an idea of a cli you
want to make or you don't want to make a
video game you don't want to make a
backing you don't want to deal with
blockchains and things even if you have
no use case for roast right now i would
still recommend to learn rust for at
least a couple of weeks
because i think that even then even if
you have no use case for rust it is
going to make you a better developer i
mean first of all you are going to have
access to a tool that is incredibly fast
and if you ever need to you're going to
be able to build incredibly fast
software but also i think that learning
rust is going to make you a better
developer outside of the ros programming
language in my case for example after
learning ros and understanding the
concept of ownership i became a better
developer outside of rust i think about
my code in a more organized way i think
about data in a different way and i find
myself that even if i'm working in go or
javascript that don't have any ownership
roles i find myself still following
those rules that even if the language
doesn't enforce the rules i pretend like
they exist because it makes my code very
easy to think about it makes me think
about the data flow of my applications
in a very different and i would say more
organized way but that's just what i
think let me know what you think are you
going to try roast uh have you tried
roast already did you like it did you
hate it what are you building with rust
why do you want to build with roast let
me know in the comments i'm going to be
looking at them right now as always
thank you for watching this video stay
happy stay free eat kimchi come champion
and see you on the next one